<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Feats>
    <Feat name="Acrobatic" type="General" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>-</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>You get a +2 bonus on all Acrobatics and Fly skill checks. If you have 10 or more ranks in one of these skills, the bonus increases to +4 for that skill.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Agile Maneuvers" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>-</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>You add your Dexterity bonus to your base attack bonus and size bonus when determining your Combat Maneuver Bonus (see Combat) instead of your Strength bonus.</Benefit>
        <Normal>You add your Strength bonus to your base attack bonus and size bonus when determining your Combat Maneuver Bonus.</Normal>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Alertness" type="General" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>-</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>You get a +2 bonus on Perception and Sense Motive skill checks. If you have 10 or more ranks in one of these skills, the bonus increases to +4 for that skill.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Alignment Channel" type="General" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Ability to channel energy.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>Instead of its normal effect, you can choose to have your ability to channel energy heal or harm outsiders of the chosen alignment subtype. You must make this choice each time you channel energy. If you choose to heal or harm creatures of the chosen alignment subtype, your channel energy has no effect on other creatures. The amount of damage healed or dealt and the DC to halve the damage is otherwise unchanged.</Benefit>
        <Special>You can gain this feat multiple times. Its effects do not stack. Each time you take this feat, it applies to a new alignment subtype. Whenever you channel energy, you must choose which type to effect.</Special>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Animal Affinity" type="General" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>-</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>You get a +2 bonus on all Handle Animal and Ride skill checks. If you have 10 or more ranks in one of these skills, the bonus increases to +4 for that skill.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Arcane Armor Training" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Light Armor Proficiency, caster level 3rd.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>As a swift action, reduce the arcane spell failure chance due to the armor you are wearing by 10% for any spells you cast this round.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Arcane Armor Mastery" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Arcane Armor Training, Medium Armor Proficiency, caster level 7th.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>As a swift action, reduce the arcane spell failure chance due to the armor you are wearing by 20% for any spells you cast this round. This bonus replaces, and does not stack with, the bonus granted by Arcane Armor Training.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Arcane Strike" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Ability to cast arcane spells.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>As a swift action, you can imbue your weapons with a fraction of your power. For 1 round, your weapons deal +1 damage and are treated as magic for the purpose of overcoming damage reduction. For every five caster levels you possess, this bonus increases by +1, to a maximum of +5 at 20th level.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Armor Proficiency, Light" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>-</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>When you wear a type of armor with which you are proficient, the armor check penalty for that armor applies only to Dexterity- and Strength-based skill checks.</Benefit>
        <Special>All characters except monks, sorcerers, and wizards automatically have Light Armor Proficiency as a bonus feat. They need not select it.</Special>
        <Normal>A character who is wearing armor with which he is not proficient applies its armor check penalty to attack rolls and to all skill checks that involve moving.</Normal>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Armor Proficiency, Medium" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Light Armor Proficiency.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>See Armor Proficiency, Light.</Benefit>
        <Special>Barbarians, clerics, druids, fighters, paladins, and rangers automatically have Medium Armor Proficiency as a bonus feat. They need not select it.</Special>
        <Normal>See Armor Proficiency, Light.</Normal>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Armor Proficiency, Heavy" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Light Armor Proficiency, Medium Armor Proficiency.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>See Armor Proficiency, Light.</Benefit>
        <Special>Fighters and paladins automatically have Heavy Armor Proficiency as a bonus feat. They need not select it.</Special>
        <Normal>See Armor Proficiency, Light.</Normal>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Athletic" type="General" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>-</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>You get a +2 bonus on Climb and Swim skill checks. If you have 10 or more ranks in one of these skills, the bonus increases to +4 for that skill.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Augment Summoning" type="General" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Spell Focus (conjuration).</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>Each creature you conjure with any summon spell gains a +4 enhancement bonus to Strength and Constitution for the duration of the spell that summoned it.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Blind-Fight" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>-</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>In melee, every time you miss because of concealment (see Combat), you can reroll your miss chance percentile roll one time to see if you actually hit.</Benefit>
        <Special>The Blind-Fight feat is of no use against a character who is the subject of a blink spell.</Special>
        <Normal>Regular attack roll modifiers for invisible attackers trying to hit you apply, and you lose your Dexterity bonus to AC. The speed reduction for darkness and poor visibility also applies.</Normal>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Catch Off-Guard" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>-</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>You do not suffer any penalties for using an improvised melee weapon. Unarmed opponents are flat-footed against any attacks you make with an improvised melee weapon.</Benefit>
        <Normal>You take a &amp;ndash;4 penalty on attack rolls made with an improvised weapon.</Normal>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Channel Smite" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Channel energy class feature.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>Before you make a melee attack roll, you can choose to spend one use of your channel energy ability as a swift action. If you channel positive energy and you hit an undead creature, that creature takes an amount of additional damage equal to the damage dealt by your channel positive energy ability. If you channel negative energy and you hit a living creature, that creature takes an amount of additional damage equal to the damage dealt by your channel negative energy ability. Your target can make a Will save, as normal, to halve this additional damage. If your attack misses, the channel energy ability is still expended with no effect.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Combat Casting" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>-</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>You get a +4 bonus on concentration checks made to cast a spell or use a spell-like ability when casting on the defensive or while grappled.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Combat Expertise" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Int 13.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>You can choose to take a &amp;ndash;1 penalty on melee attack rolls and combat maneuver checks to gain a +1 dodge bonus to your Armor Class. When your base attack bonus reaches +4, and every +4 thereafter, the penalty increases by &amp;ndash;1 and the dodge bonus increases by +1. You can only choose to use this feat when you declare that you are making an attack or a full-attack action with a melee weapon. The effects of this feat last until your next turn.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Improved Disarm" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Int 13, Combat Expertise.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>You do not provoke an attack of opportunity when performing a disarm combat maneuver. In addition, you receive a +2 bonus on checks made to disarm a foe. You also receive a +2 bonus to your Combat Maneuver Defense whenever an opponent tries to disarm you.</Benefit>
        <Normal>You provoke an attack of opportunity when performing a disarm combat maneuver.</Normal>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Greater Disarm" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Combat Expertise, Improved Disarm, base attack bonus +6, Int 13.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>You receive a +2 bonus on checks made to disarm a foe. This bonus stacks with the bonus granted by Improved Disarm. Whenever you successfully disarm an opponent, the weapon lands 15 feet away from its previous wielder, in a random direction.</Benefit>
        <Normal>Disarmed weapons and gear land at the feet of the disarmed creature.</Normal>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Improved Feint" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Int 13, Combat Expertise.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>You can make a Bluff check to feint in combat as a move action.</Benefit>
        <Normal>Feinting in combat is a standard action.</Normal>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Greater Feint" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Combat Expertise, Improved Feint, base attack bonus +6, Int 13.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>Whenever you use feint to cause an opponent to lose his Dexterity bonus, he loses that bonus until the beginning of your next turn, in addition to losing his Dexterity bonus against your next attack.</Benefit>
        <Normal>A creature you feint loses its Dexterity bonus against your next attack.</Normal>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Improved Trip" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Int 13, Combat Expertise.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>You do not provoke an attack of opportunity when performing a trip combat maneuver. In addition, you receive a +2 bonus on checks made to trip a foe. You also receive a +2 bonus to your Combat Maneuver Defense whenever an opponent tries to trip you.</Benefit>
        <Normal>You provoke an attack of opportunity when performing a trip combat maneuver.</Normal>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Greater Trip" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Combat Expertise, Improved Trip, base attack bonus +6, Int 13.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>You receive a +2 bonus on checks made to trip a foe. This bonus stacks with the bonus granted by Improved Trip. Whenever you successfully trip an opponent, that opponent provokes attacks of opportunity.</Benefit>
        <Normal>Creatures do not provoke attacks of opportunity from being tripped.</Normal>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Whirlwind Attack" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Dex 13, Int 13, Combat Expertise, Dodge, Mobility, Spring Attack, base attack bonus +4.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>When you use the full-attack action, you can give up your regular attacks and instead make one melee attack at your highest base attack bonus against each opponent within reach. You must make a separate attack roll against each opponent.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Combat Reflexes" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>-</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>You may make a number of additional attacks of opportunity per round equal to your Dexterity bonus. With this feat, you may also make attacks of opportunity while flat-footed.</Benefit>
        <Special>The Combat Reflexes feat does not allow a rogue to use her opportunist ability more than once per round.</Special>
        <Normal>A character without this feat can make only one attack of opportunity per round and can't make attacks of opportunity while flat-footed.</Normal>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Stand Still" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Combat Reflexes.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>When a foe provokes an attack of opportunity due to moving through your adjacent squares, you can make a combat maneuver check as your attack of opportunity. If successful, the enemy cannot move for the rest of his turn. An enemy can still take the rest of his action, but cannot move. This feat also applies to any creature that attempts to move from a square that is adjacent to you if such movement provokes an attack of opportunity.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Command Undead" type="General" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Channel negative energy class feature.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>As a standard action, you can use one of your uses of channel negative energy to enslave undead within 30 feet. Undead receive a Will save to negate the effect. The DC for this Will save is equal to 10 + 1/2 your cleric level + your Charisma modifier. Undead that fail their saves fall under your control, obeying your commands to the best of their ability, as if under the effects of control undead. Intelligent undead receive a new saving throw each day to resist your command. You can control any number of undead, so long as their total Hit Dice do not exceed your cleric level. If you use channel energy in this way, it has no other effect (it does not heal or harm nearby creatures). If an undead creature is under the control of another creature, you must make an opposed Charisma check whenever your orders conflict.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Critical Focus" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Base attack bonus +9.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>You receive a +4 circumstance bonus on attack rolls made to confirm critical hits.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Bleeding Critical" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Critical Focus, base attack bonus +11.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>Whenever you score a critical hit with a slashing or piercing weapon, your opponent takes 2d6 points of bleed damage (see Conditions) each round on his turn, in addition to the damage dealt by the critical hit. Bleed damage can be stopped by a DC 15 Heal skill check or through any magical healing. The effects of this feat stack.</Benefit>
        <Special>You can only apply the effects of one critical feat to a given critical hit unless you possess Critical Mastery.</Special>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Blinding Critical" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Critical Focus, base attack bonus +15.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>Whenever you score a critical hit, your opponent is permanently blinded. A successful Fortitude save reduces this to dazzled for 1d4 rounds. The DC of this Fortitude save is equal to 10 + your base attack bonus. This feat has no effect on creatures that do not rely on eyes for sight or creatures with more than two eyes (although multiple critical hits might cause blindness, at the GM's discretion). Blindness can be cured by heal, regeneration, remove blindness, or similar abilities.</Benefit>
        <Special>You can only apply the effects of one critical feat to a given critical hit unless you possess Critical Mastery.</Special>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Critical Mastery" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Critical Focus, any two critical feats, 14th-level fighter.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>When you score a critical hit, you can apply the effects of two critical feats in addition to the damage dealt.</Benefit>
        <Normal>You can only apply the effects of one critical feat to a given critical hit in addition to the damage dealt.</Normal>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Deafening Critical" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Critical Focus, base attack bonus +13.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>Whenever you score a critical hit against an opponent, the victim is permanently deafened. A successful Fortitude save reduces the deafness to 1 round. The DC of this Fortitude save is equal to 10 + your base attack bonus. This feat has no effect on deaf creatures. This deafness can be cured by heal, regeneration, remove deafness, or a similar ability.</Benefit>
        <Special>You can only apply the effects of one critical feat to a given critical hit unless you possess Critical Mastery.</Special>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Sickening Critical" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Critical Focus, base attack bonus +11.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>Whenever you score a critical hit, your opponent becomes sickened for 1 minute. The effects of this feat do not stack. Additional hits instead add to the effect's duration.</Benefit>
        <Special>You can only apply the effects of one critical feat to a given critical hit unless you possess Critical Mastery.</Special>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Staggering Critical" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Critical Focus, base attack bonus +13.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>Whenever you score a critical hit, your opponent becomes staggered for 1d4+1 rounds. A successful Fortitude save reduces the duration to 1 round. The DC of this Fortitude save is equal to 10 + your base attack bonus. The effects of this feat do not stack. Additional hits instead add to the duration.</Benefit>
        <Special>You can only apply the effects of one critical feat to a given critical hit unless you possess Critical Mastery.</Special>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Stunning Critical" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Critical Focus, Staggering Critical, base attack bonus +17.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>Whenever you score a critical hit, your opponent becomes stunned for 1d4 rounds. A successful Fortitude save reduces this to staggered for 1d4 rounds. The DC of this Fortitude save is equal to 10 + your base attack bonus. The effects of this feat do not stack. Additional hits instead add to the duration.</Benefit>
        <Special>You can only apply the effects of one critical feat to a given critical hit unless you possess Critical Mastery.</Special>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Tiring Critical" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Critical Focus, base attack bonus +13.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>Whenever you score a critical hit, your opponent becomes fatigued. This feat has no additional effect on a fatigued or exhausted creature.</Benefit>
        <Special>You can only apply the effects of one critical feat to a given critical hit unless you possess Critical Mastery.</Special>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Exhausting Critical" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Critical Focus, Tiring Critical, base attack bonus +15.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>When you score a critical hit on a foe, your target immediately becomes exhausted. This feat has no effect on exhausted creatures.</Benefit>
        <Special>You can only apply the effects of one critical feat to a given critical hit unless you possess the Critical Mastery feat.</Special>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Deadly Aim" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Dex 13, base attack bonus +1.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>You can choose to take a &amp;ndash;1 penalty on all ranged attack rolls to gain a +2 bonus on all ranged damage rolls. When your base attack bonus reaches +4, and every +4 thereafter, the penalty increases by &amp;ndash;1 and the bonus to damage increases by +2. You must choose to use this feat before making an attack roll and its effects last until your next turn. The bonus damage does not apply to touch attacks or effects that do not deal hit point damage.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Deceitful" type="General" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>-</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>You get a +2 bonus on all Bluff and Disguise skill checks. If you have 10 or more ranks in one of these skills, the bonus increases to +4 for that skill.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Defensive Combat Training" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>-</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>You treat your total Hit Dice as your base attack bonus when calculating your Combat Maneuver Defense (see Combat).</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Deft Hands" type="General" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>-</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>You get a +2 bonus on Disable Device and Sleight of Hand skill checks. If you have 10 or more ranks in one of these skills, the bonus increases to +4 for that skill.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Disruptive" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>6th-level fighter.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>The DC to cast spells defensively increases by +4 for all enemies that are within your threatened area. This increase to casting spells defensively only applies if you are aware of the enemy's location and are capable of taking an attack of opportunity. If you can only take one attack of opportunity per round and have already used that attack, this increase does not apply.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Spellbreaker" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Disruptive, 10th-level fighter.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>Enemies in your threatened area that fail their checks to cast spells defensively provoke attacks of opportunity from you.</Benefit>
        <Normal>Enemies that fail to cast spells defensively do not provoke attacks of opportunity.</Normal>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Dodge" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Dex 13.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>You gain a +1 dodge bonus to your AC. A condition that makes you lose your Dex bonus to AC also makes you lose the benefits of this feat.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Mobility" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Dex 13, Dodge.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>You get a +4 dodge bonus to Armor Class against attacks of opportunity caused when you move out of or within a threatened area. A condition that makes you lose your Dexterity bonus to Armor Class (if any) also makes you lose dodge bonuses.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Spring Attack" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Dex 13, Dodge, Mobility, base attack bonus +4.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>As a full-round action, you can move up to your speed and make a single melee attack without provoking any attacks of opportunity from the target of your attack. You can move both before and after the attack, but you must move at least 10 feet before the attack and the total distance that you move cannot be greater than your speed. You cannot use this ability to attack a foe that is adjacent to you at the start of your turn.</Benefit>
        <Normal>You cannot move before and after an attack.</Normal>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Wind Stance" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Dex 15, Dodge, base attack bonus +6.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>If you move more than 5 feet this turn, you gain 20% concealment for 1 round against ranged attacks.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Lightning Stance" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Dex 17, Dodge, Wind Stance, base attack bonus +11.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>If you take two actions to move or a withdraw action in a turn, you gain 50% concealment for 1 round.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Elemental Channel" type="General" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Channel energy class feature.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>Instead of its normal effect, you can choose to have your ability to channel energy heal or harm outsiders of your chosen elemental subtype. You must make this choice each time you channel energy. If you choose to heal or harm creatures of your elemental subtype, your channel energy has no affect on other creatures. The amount of damage healed or dealt and the DC to halve the damage is otherwise unchanged.</Benefit>
        <Special>You can gain this feat multiple times. Its effects do not stack. Each time you take this feat, it applies to a new elemental subtype.</Special>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Endurance" type="General" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>-</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>You gain a +4 bonus on the following checks and saves: Swim checks made to resist nonlethal damage from exhaustion; Constitution checks made to continue running; Constitution checks made to avoid nonlethal damage from a forced march; Constitution checks made to hold your breath; Constitution checks made to avoid nonlethal damage from starvation or thirst; Fortitude saves made to avoid nonlethal damage from hot or cold environments; and Fortitude saves made to resist damage from suffocation.</Benefit>
        <Normal>A character without this feat who sleeps in medium or heavier armor is fatigued the next day.</Normal>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Diehard" type="General" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Endurance.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>When your hit point total is below 0, but you are not dead, you automatically stabilize. You do not need to make a Constitution check each round to avoid losing additional hit points. You may choose to act as if you were disabled, rather than dying. You must make this decision as soon as you are reduced to negative hit points (even if it isn't your turn). If you do not choose to act as if you were disabled, you immediately fall unconscious.</Benefit>
        <Normal>A character without this feat who is reduced to negative hit points is unconscious and dying.</Normal>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Eschew Materials" type="General" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>-</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>You can cast any spell with a material component costing 1 gp or less without needing that component. The casting of the spell still provokes attacks of opportunity as normal. If the spell requires a material component that costs more than 1 gp, you must have the material component on hand to cast the spell, as normal.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Exotic Weapon Proficiency" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Base attack bonus +1.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>You make attack rolls with the weapon normally.</Benefit>
        <Special>You can gain Exotic Weapon Proficiency multiple times. Each time you take the feat, it applies to a new type of exotic weapon.</Special>
        <Normal>A character who uses a weapon with which he is not proficient takes a &amp;ndash;4 penalty on attack rolls.</Normal>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Extra Channel" type="General" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Channel energy class feature.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>You can channel energy two additional times per day.</Benefit>
        <Special>If a paladin with the ability to channel positive energy takes this feat, she can use lay on hands four additional times a day, but only to channel positive energy.</Special>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Extra Ki" type="General" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Ki pool class feature.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>Your ki pool increases by 2.</Benefit>
        <Special>You can gain Extra Ki multiple times. Its effects stack.</Special>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Extra Lay On Hands" type="General" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Lay on hands class feature.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>You can use your lay on hands ability two additional times per day.</Benefit>
        <Special>You can gain Extra Lay On Hands multiple times. Its effects stack.</Special>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Extra Mercy" type="General" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Lay on hands class feature, mercy class feature.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>Select one additional mercy for which you qualify. When you use lay on hands to heal damage to one target, it also receives the additional effects of this mercy.</Benefit>
        <Special>You can gain this feat multiple times. Its effects do not stack. Each time you take this feat, select a new mercy.</Special>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Extra Performance" type="General" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Bardic performance class feature.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>You can use bardic performance for 6 additional rounds per day.</Benefit>
        <Special>You can gain Extra Performance multiple times. Its effects stack.</Special>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Extra Rage" type="General" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Rage class feature.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>You can rage for 6 additional rounds per day.</Benefit>
        <Special>You can gain Extra Rage multiple times. Its effects stack.</Special>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Fleet" type="General" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>-</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>While you are wearing light or no armor, your base speed increases by 5 feet. You lose the benefits of this feat if you carry a medium or heavy load.</Benefit>
        <Special>You can take this feat multiple times. The effects stack.</Special>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Great Fortitude" type="General" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>-</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>You get a +2 bonus on all Fortitude saving throws.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Improved Great Fortitude" type="General" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Great Fortitude.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>Once per day, you may reroll a Fortitude save. You must decide to use this ability before the results are revealed. You must take the second roll, even if it is worse.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Improved Channel" type="General" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Channel energy class feature.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>Add 2 to the DC of saving throws made to resist the effects of your channel energy ability.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Improved Counterspell" type="General" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>-</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>When counterspelling, you may use a spell of the same school that is one or more spell levels higher than the target spell.</Benefit>
        <Normal>Without this feat, you may counter a spell only with the same spell or with a spell specifically designated as countering the target spell.</Normal>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Improved Critical" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Proficient with weapon, base attack bonus +8.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>When using the weapon you selected, your threat range is doubled.</Benefit>
        <Special>You can gain Improved Critical multiple times. The effects do not stack. Each time you take the feat, it applies to a new type of weapon.</Special>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Improved Familiar" type="General" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Ability to acquire a new familiar, compatible alignment, sufficiently high level (see below).</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>When choosing a familiar, the creatures listed below are also available to you. You may choose a familiar with an alignment up to one step away on each alignment axis (lawful through chaotic, good through evil).</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Improved Initiative" type="General" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>-</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>You get a +4 bonus on initiative checks.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Improved Unarmed Strike" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>-</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>You are considered to be armed even when unarmed&amp;mdash;you do not provoke attacks of opportunity when you attack foes while unarmed. Your unarmed strikes can deal lethal or nonlethal damage, at your choice.</Benefit>
        <Normal>Without this feat, you are considered unarmed when attacking with an unarmed strike, and you can deal only nonlethal damage with such an attack.</Normal>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Deflect Arrows" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Dex 13, Improved Unarmed Strike.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>You must have at least one hand free (holding nothing) to use this feat. Once per round when you would normally be hit with an attack from a ranged weapon, you may deflect it so that you take no damage from it. You must be aware of the attack and not flat-footed. Attempting to deflect a ranged attack doesn't count as an action. Unusually massive ranged weapons (such as boulders or ballista bolts) and ranged attacks generated by natural attacks or spell effects can't be deflected.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Snatch Arrows" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Dex 15, Deflect Arrows, Improved Unarmed Strike.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>When using the Deflect Arrows feat you may choose to catch the weapon instead of just deflecting it. Thrown weapons can immediately be thrown back as an attack against the original attacker (even though it isn't your turn) or kept for later use.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Improved Grapple" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Dex 13, Improved Unarmed Strike.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>You do not provoke an attack of opportunity when performing a grapple combat maneuver. In addition, you receive a +2 bonus on checks made to grapple a foe. You also receive a +2 bonus to your Combat Maneuver Defense whenever an opponent tries to grapple you.</Benefit>
        <Normal>You provoke an attack of opportunity when performing a grapple combat maneuver.</Normal>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Greater Grapple" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Improved Grapple, Improved Unarmed Strike, base attack bonus +6, Dex 13.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>You receive a +2 bonus on checks made to grapple a foe. This bonus stacks with the bonus granted by Improved Grapple. Once you have grappled a creature, maintaining the grapple is a move action. This feat allows you to make two grapple checks each round (to move, harm, or pin your opponent), but you are not required to make two checks. You only need to succeed at one of these checks to maintain the grapple.</Benefit>
        <Normal>Maintaining a grapple is a standard action.</Normal>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Scorpion Style" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Improved Unarmed Strike.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>To use this feat, you must make a single unarmed attack as a standard action. If this unarmed attack hits, you deal damage normally, and the target's base land speed is reduced to 5 feet for a number of rounds equal to your Wisdom modifier unless it makes a Fortitude saving throw (DC 10 + 1/2 your character level + your Wis modifier).</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Gorgon's Fist" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Improved Unarmed Strike, Scorpion Style, base attack bonus +6.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>As a standard action, make a single unarmed melee attack against a foe whose speed is reduced (such as from Scorpion Style). If the attack hits, you deal damage normally and the target is staggered until the end of your next turn unless it makes a Fortitude saving throw (DC 10 + 1/2 your character level + your Wis modifier). This feat has no effect on targets that are staggered.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Medusa's Wrath" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Improved Unarmed Strike, Gorgon's Fist, Scorpion Style, base attack bonus +11.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>Whenever you use the full-attack action and make at least one unarmed strike, you can make two additional unarmed strikes at your highest base attack bonus. These bonus attacks must be made against a dazed, flat-footed, paralyzed, staggered, stunned, or unconscious foe.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Stunning Fist" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Dex 13, Wis 13, Improved Unarmed Strike, base attack bonus +8.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>You must declare that you are using this feat before you make your attack roll (thus, a failed attack roll ruins the attempt). Stunning Fist forces a foe damaged by your unarmed attack to make a Fortitude saving throw (DC 10 + 1/2 your character level + your Wis modifier), in addition to dealing damage normally. A defender who fails this saving throw is stunned for 1 round (until just before your next turn). A stunned character drops everything held, can't take actions, loses any Dexterity bonus to AC, and takes a &amp;ndash;2 penalty to AC. You may attempt a stunning attack once per day for every four levels you have attained (but see Special), and no more than once per round. Constructs, oozes, plants, undead, incorporeal creatures, and creatures immune to critical hits cannot be stunned.</Benefit>
        <Special>A monk receives Stunning Fist as a bonus feat at 1st level, even if he does not meet the prerequisites. A monk may attempt a stunning attack a number of times per day equal to his monk level, plus one more time per day for every four levels he has in classes other than monk.</Special>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Improvised Weapon Mastery" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Catch Off-Guard or Throw Anything, base attack bonus +8.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>You do not suffer any penalties for using an improvised weapon. Increase the amount of damage dealt by the improvised weapon by one step (for example, 1d4 becomes 1d6) to a maximum of 1d8 (2d6 if the improvised weapon is two-handed). The improvised weapon has a critical threat range of 19&amp;ndash;20, with a critical multiplier of &amp;times;2.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Intimidating Prowess" type="General" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>-</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>Add your Strength modifier to Intimidate skill checks in addition to your Charisma modifier.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Iron Will" type="General" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>-</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>You get a +2 bonus on all Will saving throws.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Improved Iron Will" type="General" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Iron Will.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>Once per day, you may reroll a Will save. You must decide to use this ability before the results are revealed. You must take the second roll, even if it is worse.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Leadership" type="General" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>-</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit />
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Lightning Reflexes" type="General" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>-</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>You get a +2 bonus on all Reflex saving throws.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Improved Lightning Reflexes" type="General" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Lightning Reflexes.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>Once per day, you may reroll a Reflex save. You must decide to use this ability before the results are revealed. You must take the second roll, even if it is worse.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Lunge" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Base attack bonus +6.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>You can increase the reach of your melee attacks by 5 feet until the end of your turn by taking a &amp;ndash;2 penalty to your AC until your next turn. You must decide to use this ability before any attacks are made.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Magical Aptitude" type="General" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>-</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>You get a +2 bonus on all Spellcraft checks and Use Magic Device checks. If you have 10 or more ranks in one of these skills, the bonus increases to +4 for that skill.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Martial Weapon Proficiency" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>-</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>You make attack rolls with the selected weapon normally (without the non-proficient penalty).</Benefit>
        <Special>Barbarians, fighters, paladins, and rangers are proficient with all martial weapons. They need not select this feat.</Special>
        <Normal>When using a weapon with which you are not proficient, you take a &amp;ndash;4 penalty on attack rolls.</Normal>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Master Craftsman" type="General" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>5 ranks in any Craft or Profession skill.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>Choose one Craft or Profession skill in which you possess at least 5 ranks. You receive a +2 bonus on your chosen Craft or Profession skill. Ranks in your chosen skill count as your caster level for the purposes of qualifying for the Craft Magic Arms and Armor and Craft Wondrous Item feats. You can create magic items using these feats, substituting your ranks in the chosen skill for your total caster level. You must use the chosen skill for the check to create the item. The DC to create the item still increases for any necessary spell requirements (see the magic item creation rules in Magic Items). You cannot use this feat to create any spell-trigger or spell-activation item.</Benefit>
        <Normal>Only spellcasters can qualify for the Craft Magic Arms and Armor and Craft Wondrous Item feats.</Normal>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Mounted Combat" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Ride 1 rank.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>Once per round when your mount is hit in combat, you may attempt a Ride check (as an immediate action) to negate the hit. The hit is negated if your Ride check result is greater than the opponent's attack roll.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Mounted Archery" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Ride 1 rank, Mounted Combat.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>The penalty you take when using a ranged weapon while mounted is halved: &amp;ndash;2 instead of &amp;ndash;4 if your mount is taking a double move, and &amp;ndash;4 instead of &amp;ndash;8 if your mount is running.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Ride-By Attack" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Ride 1 rank, Mounted Combat.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>When you are mounted and use the charge action, you may move and attack as if with a standard charge and then move again (continuing the straight line of the charge). Your total movement for the round can't exceed double your mounted speed. You and your mount do not provoke an attack of opportunity from the opponent that you attack.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Spirited Charge" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Ride 1 rank, Mounted Combat, Ride-By Attack.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>When mounted and using the charge action, you deal double damage with a melee weapon (or triple damage with a lance).</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Trample" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Ride 1 rank, Mounted Combat.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>When you attempt to overrun an opponent while mounted, your target may not choose to avoid you. Your mount may make one hoof attack against any target you knock down, gaining the standard +4 bonus on attack rolls against prone targets.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Unseat" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Str 13, Ride 1 rank, Mounted Combat, Power Attack, Improved Bull Rush, base attack bonus +1.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>When charging an opponent while mounted and wielding a lance, resolve the attack as normal. If it hits, you may immediately make a free bull rush attempt in addition to the normal damage. If successful, the target is knocked off his horse and lands prone in a space adjacent to his mount that is directly away from you.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Natural Spell" type="General" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Wis 13, wild shape class feature.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>You can complete the verbal and somatic components of spells while using wild shape. You substitute various noises and gestures for the normal verbal and somatic components of a spell.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Nimble Moves" type="General" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Dex 13.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>Whenever you move, you may move through 5 feet of difficult terrain each round as if it were normal terrain. This feat allows you to take a 5-foot step into difficult terrain.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Acrobatic Steps" type="General" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Dex 15, Nimble Moves.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>Whenever you move, you may move through up to 15 feet of difficult terrain each round as if it were normal terrain. The effects of this feat stack with those provided by Nimble Moves (allowing you to move normally through a total of 20 feet of difficult terrain each round).</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Persuasive" type="General" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>-</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>You get a +2 bonus on Diplomacy and Intimidate skill checks. If you have 10 or more ranks in one of these skills, the bonus increases to +4 for that skill.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Point-Blank Shot" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>-</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>You get a +1 bonus on attack and damage rolls with ranged weapons at ranges of up to 30 feet.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Far Shot" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Point-Blank Shot.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>You only suffer a &amp;ndash;1 penalty per full range increment between you and your target when using a ranged weapon.</Benefit>
        <Normal>You suffer a &amp;ndash;2 penalty per full range increment between you and your target.</Normal>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Precise Shot" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Point-Blank Shot.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>You can shoot or throw ranged weapons at an opponent engaged in melee without taking the standard &amp;ndash;4 penalty on your attack roll.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Improved PreciseShot" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Dex 19, Point-Blank Shot, Precise Shot, base attack bonus +11.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>Your ranged attacks ignore the AC bonus granted to targets by anything less than total cover, and the miss chance granted to targets by anything less than total concealment. Total cover and total concealment provide their normal benefits against your ranged attacks.</Benefit>
        <Normal>See the normal rules on the effects of cover and concealment in Combat.</Normal>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Pinpoint Targeting" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Dex 19, Improved Precise Shot, Point-Blank Shot, Precise Shot, base attack bonus +16.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>As a standard action, make a single ranged attack. The target does not gain any armor, natural armor, or shield bonuses to its Armor Class. You do not gain the benefit of this feat if you move this round.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Shot on the Run" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Dex 13, Dodge, Mobility, Point-Blank Shot, base attack bonus +4.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>As a full-round action, you can move up to your speed and make a single ranged attack at any point during your movement.</Benefit>
        <Normal>You cannot move before and after an attack with a ranged weapon.</Normal>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Rapid Shot" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Dex 13, Point-Blank Shot.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>When making a full-attack action with a ranged weapon, you can fire one additional time this round. All of your attack rolls take a &amp;ndash;2 penalty when using Rapid Shot.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Manyshot" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Dex 17, Point-Blank Shot, Rapid Shot, base attack bonus +6.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>When making a full-attack action with a bow, your first attack fires two arrows. If the attack hits, both arrows hit. Apply precision-based damage (such as sneak attack) and critical hit damage only once for this attack. Damage bonuses from using a composite bow with a high Strength bonus apply to each arrow, as do other damage bonuses, such as a ranger's favored enemy bonus. Damage reduction and resistances apply separately to each arrow.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Power Attack" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Str 13, base attack bonus +1.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>You can choose to take a &amp;ndash;1 penalty on all melee attack rolls and combat maneuver checks to gain a +2 bonus on all melee damage rolls. This bonus to damage is increased by half (+50%) if you are making an attack with a two-handed weapon, a one handed weapon using two hands, or a primary natural weapon that adds 1-1/2 times your Strength modifier on damage rolls. This bonus to damage is halved (&amp;ndash;50%) if you are making an attack with an off-hand weapon or secondary natural weapon. When your base attack bonus reaches +4, and every 4 points thereafter, the penalty increases by &amp;ndash;1 and the bonus to damage increases by +2. You must choose to use this feat before making an attack roll, and its effects last until your next turn. The bonus damage does not apply to touch attacks or effects that do not deal hit point damage.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Cleave" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Str 13, Power Attack, base attack bonus +1.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>As a standard action, you can make a single attack at your full base attack bonus against a foe within reach. If you hit, you deal damage normally and can make an additional attack (using your full base attack bonus) against a foe that is adjacent to the first and also within reach. You can only make one additional attack per round with this feat. When you use this feat, you take a &amp;ndash;2 penalty to your Armor Class until your next turn.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Great Cleave" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Str 13, Cleave, Power Attack, base attack bonus +4.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>As a standard action, you can make a single attack at your full base attack bonus against a foe within reach. If you hit, you deal damage normally and can make an additional attack (using your full base attack bonus) against a foe that is adjacent to the previous foe and also within reach. If you hit, you can continue to make attacks against foes adjacent to the previous foe, so long as they are within your reach. You cannot attack an individual foe more than once during this attack action. When you use this feat, you take a &amp;ndash;2 penalty to your Armor Class until your next turn.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Improved Bull Rush" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Str 13, Power Attack, base attack bonus +1.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>You do not provoke an attack of opportunity when performing a bull rush combat maneuver. In addition, you receive a +2 bonus on checks made to bull rush a foe. You also receive a +2 bonus to your Combat Maneuver Defense whenever an opponent tries to bull rush you.</Benefit>
        <Normal>You provoke an attack of opportunity when performing a bull rush combat maneuver.</Normal>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Greater Bull Rush" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Improved Bull Rush, Power Attack, base attack bonus +6, Str 13.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>You receive a +2 bonus on checks made to bull rush a foe. This bonus stacks with the bonus granted by Improved Bull Rush. Whenever you bull rush an opponent, his movement provokes attacks of opportunity from all of your allies (but not you).</Benefit>
        <Normal>Creatures moved by bull rush do not provoke attacks of opportunity.</Normal>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Improved Overrun" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Str 13, Power Attack, base attack bonus +1.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>You do not provoke an attack of opportunity when performing an overrun combat maneuver. In addition, you receive a +2 bonus on checks made to overrrun a foe. You also receive a +2 bonus to your Combat Maneuver Defense whenever an opponent tries to overrun you. Targets of your overrun attempt may not chose to avoid you.</Benefit>
        <Normal>You provoke an attack of opportunity when performing an overrun combat maneuver.</Normal>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Greater Overrun" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Improved Overrun, Power Attack, base attack bonus +6, Str 13.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>You receive a +2 bonus on checks made to overrun a foe. This bonus stacks with the bonus granted by Improved Overrun. Whenever you overrun opponents, they provoke attacks of opportunity if they are knocked prone by your overrun.</Benefit>
        <Normal>Creatures knocked prone by your overrun do not provoke an attack of opportunity.</Normal>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Improved Sunder" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Str 13, Power Attack, base attack bonus +1.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>You do not provoke an attack of opportunity when performing a sunder combat maneuver. In addition, you receive a +2 bonus on checks made to sunder an item. You also receive a +2 bonus to your Combat Maneuver Defense whenever an opponent tries to sunder your gear.</Benefit>
        <Normal>You provoke an attack of opportunity when performing a sunder combat maneuver.</Normal>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Greater Sunder" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Improved Sunder, Power Attack, base attack bonus +6, Str 13.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>You receive a +2 bonus on checks made to sunder an item. This bonus stacks with the bonus granted by Improved Sunder. Whenever you sunder to destroy a weapon, shield, or suit of armor, any excess damage is applied to the item's wielder. No damage is transferred if you decide to leave the item with 1 hit point.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Quick Draw" type="General" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Base attack bonus +1.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>You can draw a weapon as a free action instead of as a move action. You can draw a hidden weapon (see the Sleight of Hand skill) as a move action.</Benefit>
        <Normal>Without this feat, you may draw a weapon as a move action, or (if your base attack bonus is +1 or higher) as a free action as part of movement. Without this feat, you can draw a hidden weapon as a standard action.</Normal>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Rapid Reload" type="General" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Weapon Proficiency (crossbow type chosen).</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>The time required for you to reload your chosen type of crossbow is reduced to a free action (for a hand or light crossbow) or a move action (for a heavy crossbow). Reloading a crossbow still provokes an attack of opportunity.</Benefit>
        <Special>You can gain Rapid Reload multiple times. Each time you take the feat, it applies to a new type of crossbow.</Special>
        <Normal>A character without this feat needs a move action to reload a hand or light crossbow, or a full-round action to reload a heavy crossbow.</Normal>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Run" type="General" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>-</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>When running, you move five times your normal speed (if wearing medium, light, or no armor and carrying no more than a medium load) or four times your speed (if wearing heavy armor or carrying a heavy load). If you make a jump after a running start (see the Acrobatics skill description), you gain a +4 bonus on your Acrobatics check. While running, you retain your Dexterity bonus to your Armor Class.</Benefit>
        <Normal>You move four times your speed while running (if wearing medium, light, or no armor and carrying no more than a medium load) or three times your speed (if wearing heavy armor or carrying a heavy load), and you lose your Dexterity bonus to AC.</Normal>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Selective Channeling" type="General" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Cha 13, channel energy class feature.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>When you channel energy, you can choose a number of targets in the area up to your Charisma modifier. These targets are not affected by your channeled energy.</Benefit>
        <Normal>All targets in a 30-foot burst are affected when you channel energy. You can only choose whether or not you are affected.</Normal>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Self-Sufficient" type="General" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>-</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>You get a +2 bonus on all Heal checks and Survival checks. If you have 10 or more ranks in one of these skills, the bonus increases to +4 for that skill.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Shield Proficiency" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>-</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>When you use a shield (except a tower shield), the shield's armor check penalty only applies to Strength- and Dexterity-based skills.</Benefit>
        <Special>Barbarians, bards, clerics, druids, fighters, paladins, and rangers all automatically have Shield Proficiency as a bonus feat. They need not select it.</Special>
        <Normal>When you are using a shield with which you are not proficient, you take the shield's armor check penalty on attack rolls and on all skill checks that involve moving.</Normal>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Improved Shield Bash" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Shield Proficiency.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>When you perform a shield bash, you may still apply the shield's shield bonus to your AC.</Benefit>
        <Normal>Without this feat, a character that performs a shield bash loses the shield's shield bonus to AC until his next turn (see Equipment).</Normal>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Shield Slam" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Improved Shield Bash, Shield Proficiency, Two-Weapon Fighting, base attack bonus +6.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>Any opponents hit by your shield bash are also hit with a free bull rush attack, substituting your attack roll for the combat maneuver check (see Combat). This bull rush does not provoke an attack of opportunity. Opponents who cannot move back due to a wall or other surface are knocked prone after moving the maximum possible distance. You may choose to move with your target if you are able to take a 5-foot step or to spend an action to move this turn.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Shield Master" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Improved Shield Bash, Shield Proficiency, Shield Slam, Two-Weapon Fighting, base attack bonus +11.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>You do not suffer any penalties on attack rolls made with a shield while you are wielding another weapon. Add your shield's enhancement bonus to attacks and damage rolls made with the shield as if it was a weapon enhancement bonus.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Shield Focus" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Shield Proficiency, base attack bonus +1.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>Increase the AC bonus granted by any shield you are using by 1.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Greater Shield Focus" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Shield Focus, Shield Proficiency, base attack bonus +1, 8th-level fighter.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>Increase the AC bonus granted by any shield you are using by 1. This bonus stacks with the bonus granted by Shield Focus.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Tower Shield Proficiency" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Shield Proficiency.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>When you use a tower shield, the shield's armor check penalty only applies to Strength and Dexterity-based skills.</Benefit>
        <Special>Fighters automatically have Tower Shield Proficiency as a bonus feat. They need not select it.</Special>
        <Normal>A character using a shield with which he is not proficient takes the shield's armor check penalty on attack rolls and on all skill checks that involve moving, including Ride.</Normal>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Simple Weapon Proficiency" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>-</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>You make attack rolls with simple weapons without penalty.</Benefit>
        <Special>All characters except for druids, monks, and wizards are automatically proficient with all simple weapons. They need not select this feat.</Special>
        <Normal>When using a weapon with which you are not proficient, you take a &amp;ndash;4 penalty on attack rolls.</Normal>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Skill Focus" type="General" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>-</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>You get a +3 bonus on all checks involving the chosen skill. If you have 10 or more ranks in that skill, this bonus increases to +6.</Benefit>
        <Special>You can gain this feat multiple times. Its effects do not stack. Each time you take the feat, it applies to a new skill.</Special>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Spell Focus" type="General" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>-</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>Add +1 to the Difficulty Class for all saving throws against spells from the school of magic you select.</Benefit>
        <Special>You can gain this feat multiple times. Its effects do not stack. Each time you take the feat, it applies to a new school of magic.</Special>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Greater Spell Focus" type="General" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Spell Focus.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>Add +1 to the Difficulty Class for all saving throws against spells from the school of magic you select. This bonus stacks with the bonus from Spell Focus.</Benefit>
        <Special>You can gain this feat multiple times. Its effects do not stack. Each time you take the feat, it applies to a new school to which you already have applied the Spell Focus feat.</Special>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Spell Mastery" type="General" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>1st-level wizard</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>Each time you take this feat, choose a number of spells that you already know equal to your Intelligence modifier. From that point on, you can prepare these spells without referring to a spellbook.</Benefit>
        <Normal>Without this feat, you must use a spellbook to prepare all your spells, except read magic.</Normal>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Spell Penetration" type="General" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>-</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>You get a +2 bonus on caster level checks (1d20 + caster level) made to overcome a creature's spell resistance.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Greater Spell Penetration" type="General" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Spell Penetration.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>You get a +2 bonus on caster level checks (1d20 + caster level) made to overcome a creature's spell resistance. This bonus stacks with the one from Spell Penetration.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Stealthy" type="General" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>-</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>You get a +2 bonus on all Escape Artist and Stealth skill checks. If you have 10 or more ranks in one of these skills, the bonus increases to +4 for that skill.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Step Up" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Base attack bonus +1.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>Whenever an adjacent foe attempts to take a 5-foot step away from you, you may also make a 5-foot step as an immediate action so long as you end up adjacent to the foe that triggered this ability. If you take this step, you cannot take a 5-foot step during your next turn. If you take an action to move during your next turn, subtract 5 feet from your total movement.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Strike Back" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Base attack bonus +11.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>You can ready an action to make a melee attack against any foe that attacks you in melee, even if the foe is outside of your reach.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Throw Anything" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>-</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>You do not suffer any penalties for using an improvised ranged weapon. You receive a +1 circumstance bonus on attack rolls made with thrown splash weapons.</Benefit>
        <Normal>You take a &amp;ndash;4 penalty on attack rolls made with an improvised weapon.</Normal>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Toughness" type="General" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>-</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>You gain +3 hit points. For every Hit Die you possess beyond 3, you gain an additional +1 hit point. If you have more than 3 Hit Dice, you gain +1 hit points whenever you gain a Hit Die (such as when you gain a level).</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Turn Undead" type="General" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Channel positive energy class feature.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>You can, as a standard action, use one of your uses of channel positive energy to cause all undead within 30 feet of you to flee, as if panicked. Undead receive a Will save to negate the effect. The DC for this Will save is equal to 10 + 1/2 your cleric level + your Charisma modifier. Undead that fail their save flee for 1 minute. Intelligent undead receive a new saving throw each round to end the effect. If you use channel energy in this way, it has no other effect (it does not heal or harm nearby creatures).</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Two-Weapon Fighting" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Dex 15.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>Your penalties on attack rolls for fighting with two weapons are reduced. The penalty for your primary hand lessens by 2 and the one for your off hand lessens by 6. See Two-Weapon Fighting in Combat.</Benefit>
        <Normal>If you wield a second weapon in your off hand, you can get one extra attack per round with that weapon. When fighting in this way you suffer a &amp;ndash;6 penalty with your regular attack or attacks with your primary hand and a &amp;ndash;10 penalty to the attack with your off hand. If your off-hand weapon is light, the penalties are reduced by 2 each. An unarmed strike is always considered light.</Normal>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Double Slice" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Dex 15, Two-Weapon Fighting.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>Add your Strength bonus to damage rolls made with your off-hand weapon.</Benefit>
        <Normal>You normally add only half of your Strength modifier to damage rolls made with a weapon wielded in your off-hand.</Normal>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Two-Weapon Rend" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Dex 17, Double Slice, Improved Two-Weapon Fighting, Two-Weapon Fighting, base attack bonus +11.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>If you hit an opponent with both your primary hand and your off-hand weapon, you deal an additional 1d10 points of damage plus 1-1/2 times your Strength modifier. You can only deal this additional damage once each round.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Improved Two-Weapon Fighting" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Dex 17, Two-Weapon Fighting, base attack bonus +6.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>In addition to the standard single extra attack you get with an off-hand weapon, you get a second attack with it, albeit at a &amp;ndash;5 penalty.</Benefit>
        <Normal>Without this feat, you can only get a single extra attack with an off-hand weapon.</Normal>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Greater Two-Weapon Fighting" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Dex 19, Improved Two-Weapon Fighting, Two-Weapon Fighting, base attack bonus +11.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>You get a third attack with your off-hand weapon, albeit at a &amp;ndash;10 penalty.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Two-Weapon Defense" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Dex 15, Two-Weapon Fighting.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>When wielding a double weapon or two weapons (not including natural weapons or unarmed strikes), you gain a +1 shield bonus to your AC.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Vital Strike" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Base attack bonus +6.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>When you use the attack action, you can make one attack at your highest base attack bonus that deals additional damage. Roll the weapon's damage dice for the attack twice and add the results together before adding bonuses from Strength, weapon abilities (such as flaming), precision based damage, and other damage bonuses. These extra weapon damage dice are not multiplied on a critical hit, but are added to the total.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Improved Vital Strike" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Vital Strike, base attack bonus +11.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>When you use the attack action, you can make one attack at your highest base attack bonus that deals additional damage. Roll the weapon's damage dice for the attack three times and add the results together before adding bonuses from Strength, weapon abilities (such as flaming), precision based damage, and other damage bonuses. These extra weapon damage dice are not multiplied on a critical hit, but are added to the total.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Greater Vital Strike" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Improved Vital Strike, Vital Strike, base attack bonus +16.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>When you use the attack action, you can make one attack at your highest base attack bonus that deals additional damage. Roll the weapon's damage dice for the attack four times and add the results together before adding bonuses from Strength, weapon abilities (such as flaming), precision based damage, and other damage bonuses. These extra weapon damage dice are not multiplied on a critical hit, but are added to the total.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Weapon Finesse" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>-</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>With a light weapon, rapier, whip, or spiked chain made for a creature of your size category, you may use your Dexterity modifier instead of your Strength modifier on attack rolls. If you carry a shield, its armor check penalty applies to your attack rolls.</Benefit>
        <Special>Natural weapons are considered light weapons.</Special>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Weapon Focus" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Proficiency with selected weapon, base attack bonus +1.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>You gain a +1 bonus on all attack rolls you make using the selected weapon.</Benefit>
        <Special>You can gain this feat multiple times. Its effects do not stack. Each time you take the feat, it applies to a new type of weapon.</Special>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Dazzling Display" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Weapon Focus, proficiency with the selected weapon.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>While wielding the weapon in which you have Weapon Focus, you can perform a bewildering show of prowess as a full-round action. Make an Intimidate check to demoralize all foes within 30 feet who can see your display.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Shatter Defenses" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Weapon Focus, Dazzling Display, base attack bonus +6, proficiency with weapon.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>Any shaken, frightened, or panicked opponent hit by you this round is flat-footed to your attacks until the end of your next turn. This includes any additional attacks you make this round.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Deadly Stroke" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Dazzling Display, Greater Weapon Focus, Shatter Defenses, Weapon Focus, proficiency with the selected weapon, base attack bonus +11.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>As a standard action, make a single attack with the weapon for which you have Greater Weapon Focus against a stunned or flat-footed opponent. If you hit, you deal double the normal damage and the target takes 1 point of Constitution bleed (see Conditions). The additional damage and bleed is not multiplied on a critical hit.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Greater Weapon Focus" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Proficiency with selected weapon, Weapon Focus with selected weapon, base attack bonus +1, 8th-level fighter.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>You gain a +1 bonus on attack rolls you make using the selected weapon. This bonus stacks with other bonuses on attack rolls, including those from Weapon Focus.</Benefit>
        <Special>You can gain Greater Weapon Focus multiple times. Its effects do not stack. Each time you take the feat, it applies to a new type of weapon.</Special>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Penetrating Strike" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Weapon Focus, base attack bonus +1, 12th-level fighter, proficiency with weapon.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>Your attacks with weapons selected with Weapon Focus ignore up to 5 points of damage reduction. This feat does not apply to damage reduction without a type (such as DR 10/&amp;mdash;).</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Greater Penetrating Strike" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Penetrating Strike, Weapon Focus, 16th-level fighter.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>Your attacks with weapons selected with Weapon Focus ignore up to 10 points of damage reduction. This amount is reduced to 5 points for damage reduction without a type (such as DR 10/&amp;mdash;).</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Weapon Specialization" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Proficiency with selected weapon, Weapon Focus with selected weapon, fighter level 4th.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>You gain a +2 bonus on all damage rolls you make using the selected weapon.</Benefit>
        <Special>You can gain this feat multiple times. Its effects do not stack. Each time you take the feat, it applies to a new type of weapon.</Special>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Greater Weapon Specialization" type="Combat" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Proficiency with selected weapon, Greater Weapon Focus with selected weapon, Weapon Focus with selected weapon, Weapon Specialization with selected weapon, 12th-level fighter.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>You gain a +2 bonus on all damage rolls you make using the selected weapon. This bonus to damage stacks with other damage roll bonuses, including any you gain from Weapon Specialization.</Benefit>
        <Special>You can gain Greater Weapon Specialization multiple times. Its effects do not stack. Each time you take the feat, it applies to a new type of weapon.</Special>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Brew Potion" type="General" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Caster level 3rd.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>You can create a potion of any 3rd-level or lower spell that you know and that targets one or more creatures or objects. Brewing a potion takes 2 hours if its base price is 250 gp or less, otherwise brewing a potion takes 1 day for each 1,000 gp in its base price. When you create a potion, you set the caster level, which must be sufficient to cast the spell in question and no higher than your own level. To brew a potion, you must use up raw materials costing one half this base price. See the magic item creation rules in Magic Items for more information.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Craft Magic Arms and Armor" type="General" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Caster level 5th.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>You can create magic weapons, armor, or shields. Enhancing a weapon, suit of armor, or shield takes 1 day for each 1,000 gp in the price of its magical features. To enhance a weapon, suit of armor, or shield, you must use up raw materials costing half of this total price. See the magic item creation rules in Magic Items for more information.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Craft Rod" type="General" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Caster level 9th.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>You can create magic rods. Crafting a rod takes 1 day for each 1,000 gp in its base price. To craft a rod, you must use up raw materials costing half of its base price. See the magic item creation rules in Magic Items for more information.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Craft Staff" type="General" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Caster level 11th.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>You can create any staff whose prerequisites you meet. Crafting a staff takes 1 day for each 1,000 gp in its base price. To craft a staff, you must use up raw materials costing half of its base price. A newly created staff has 10 charges. See the magic item creation rules in Magic Items for more information.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Craft Wand" type="General" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Caster level 5th.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>You can create a wand of any 4th-level or lower spell that you know. Crafting a wand takes 1 day for each 1,000 gp in its base price. To craft a wand, you must use up raw materials costing half of this base price. A newly created wand has 50 charges. See the magic item creation rules in Magic Items for more information.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Craft Wondrous Item" type="General" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Caster level 3rd.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>You can create a wide variety of magic wondrous items. Crafting a wondrous item takes 1 day for each 1,000 gp in its price. To create a wondrous item, you must use up raw materials costing half of its base price. See the magic item creation rules in Magic Items for more information.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Forge Ring" type="General" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Caster level 7th.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>You can create magic rings. Crafting a ring takes 1 day for each 1,000 gp in its base price. To craft a ring, you must use up raw materials costing half of the base price. See the magic item creation rules in Magic Items for more information.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Scribe Scroll" type="General" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>Caster level 1st.</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>You can create a scroll of any spell that you know. Scribing a scroll takes 2 hours if its base price is 250 gp or less, otherwise scribing a scroll takes 1 day for each 1,000 gp in its base price. To scribe a scroll, you must use up raw materials costing half of this base price. See the magic item creation rules in Magic Items for more information.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Empower Spell" type="Metamagic" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>-</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>All variable, numeric effects of an empowered spell are increased by half, including bonuses to those dice rolls.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Enlarge Spell" type="Metamagic" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>-</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>You can alter a spell with a range of close, medium, or long to increase its range by 100%. An enlarged spell with a range of close now has a range of 50 ft. + 5 ft./level, while medium-range spells have a range of 200 ft. + 20 ft./level and long-range spells have a range of 800 ft. + 80 ft./level. An enlarged spell uses up a spell slot one level higher than the spell's actual level.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Extend Spell" type="Metamagic" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>-</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>An extended spell lasts twice as long as normal. A spell with a duration of concentration, instantaneous, or permanent is not affected by this feat. An extended spell uses up a spell slot one level higher than the spell's actual level.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Heighten Spell" type="Metamagic" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>-</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>A heightened spell has a higher spell level than normal (up to a maximum of 9th level). Unlike other metamagic feats, Heighten Spell actually increases the effective level of the spell that it modifies. All effects dependent on spell level (such as saving throw DCs and ability to penetrate a lesser globe of invulnerability) are calculated according to the heightened level. The heightened spell is as difficult to prepare and cast as a spell of its effective level.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Maximize Spell" type="Metamagic" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>-</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>All variable, numeric effects of a spell modified by this feat are maximized. Saving throws and opposed rolls are not affected, nor are spells without random variables. A maximized spell uses up a spell slot three levels higher than the spell's actual level.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Quicken Spell" type="Metamagic" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>-</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>Casting a quickened spell is a swift action. You can perform another action, even casting another spell, in the same round as you cast a quickened spell. A spell whose casting time is more than 1 round or 1 full-round action cannot be quickened.</Benefit>
        <Special>You can apply the effects of this feat to a spell cast spontaneously, so long as it has a casting time that is not more than 1 full-round action, without increasing the spell's casting time.</Special>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Silent Spell" type="Metamagic" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>-</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>A silent spell can be cast with no verbal components. Spells without verbal components are not affected. A silent spell uses up a spell slot one level higher than the spell's actual level.</Benefit>
        <Special>Bard spells cannot be enhanced by this feat.</Special>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Still Spell" type="Metamagic" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>-</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>A stilled spell can be cast with no somatic components. Spells without somatic components are not affected. A stilled spell uses up a spell slot one level higher than the spell's actual level.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
    <Feat name="Widen Spell" type="Metamagic" source="Core">
        <Prerequisites>-</Prerequisites>
        <Benefit>You can alter a burst, emanation, or spread-shaped spell to increase its area. Any numeric measurements of the spell's area increase by 100%. A widened spell uses up a spell slot three levels higher than the spell's actual level.</Benefit>
    </Feat>
</Feats>